UPASANA RATHORE

Marital Status: Single Contact No: 8956203232

DOB-3rd March'1985 Email: rathoreupasana@gmail.com

HUMAN RESOURCE PROFESSIONAL

A motivated and result-focused Human Resource Professional, seeking an opportunity to utilize my skill and education to contribute to employer objectives and success with a company offering for challenge and growth. With over 17 years of dynamic experience in BPO, Education, Real Estate, Manufacturing, IT Company and HR experience of 12 years. Handled recruitment of senior level management, mid-level management, junior level hiring and overall handling the HR Operations of full employee life cycle from on-boarding to F&F settlements and Administration Manager handling all the operational and administrative responsibilities.

HR SKILLS

- Planning & Organizing
- Talent Acquisition
- Non IT/IT Recruitment
- Rewards & Recognition
- Team Management
- On boarding & Off-boarding
- Payroll Management
- Leave & Attendance Management
- Policy Formulation & Implementation
- Performance Management/Appraisals
- HR Records Management
- Statutory Compliance
- Full n Final Settlements
- Exit Formalities
- Employee Relations

ADMIN RESPONSIBILITIES

Facilities Management: Supervision and Managing Housekeeping Activities, attendance control & manpower allocation for: Housekeeping, Reception, Front office, Cafeteria, Canteen & Pantry services.

Vendor Management: Vendor Negotiations. Verification of bills submitted by vendors and making the payments. Inviting quotation and negotiation with vendors for purchase of office requirements.

Telecommunication: Procurement of new Telephone lines for board, mobile sim-cards & Data Card.

Budgeting & Expense Management: Preparation of projected and monthly expenditure plan i.e yearly budgets.

Work Experience:

Hotel Shraddha Inn, Shirdi
Aeon Software Pvt. Ltd., Pune(Software)
HR & Admin Manager Jan 27th 2018 to till date
HR Manager Jan 1st 2016 to Jan 25th 2018
HR Manager May 19th 2014 to 29th Dec'2015
Positive Metering Pumps (I) Pvt. Ltd, Nashik(Mfg.)
Assistant HR, July 17th 2013 to 18th May'2014

Ashoka Universal School (International School, ICSE Board), Nashik.

Personal Assistant (PA) to Sr. Headmistress & Activity Headmistress, - June 26th 2009 to June 2013

- Maintaining daily appointments
- Scheduling meetings
- Handling paper work, files, etc.
- Drafting letters, Mails etc.
- Preparing PowerPoint Presentations
- Preparing circulars, notices, etc.
- Preparing class time table, workload of educators, educators time table, etc.
- Preparing budget
- Preparing agendas
- Handled international school affiliation of two branches.
- Handling events/functions.

Plexus Network of Nerves Pvt. Ltd. (Call Center), Nashik

Customer Sales Executive (C.S.E.) (U.S. & U.K. process), Feb. 8th 2007- May 31st 2008

De-Quest International Call Web (Call Center), Nashik

Customer Sales Executive (C.S.E.) (Australian process), May 2nd 2006-Dec. 6th 2006

Responsibilities and Duties

Recruitment, Selection & Manpower Planning

- Preparing job descriptions for every position.
- Resourcing, screening and short listing resumes through various job portals based on the job requirement.
- Manage the hiring process like sourcing, screening & shortlisting candidates through different job portals (Indeed, Monster, Naukri, LinkedIn), interviewing (F2F, telephonic, Video-Skype, Google Meet, Zoom) background verification assessing, and selection for the position.
- Responsible for recruitment of all levels from different departments.(Technical and Non-Technical).
- Conducting telephone and Personal interviews with the Department heads
- Organizing recruitment process.
- Creating a resume database.
- Maintaining the record of recruitment as well as resignation details. Conducting exit interviews & managing full & final settlements as per the SLA.
- Facilitate the hiring, onboarding, and capability development of the employees.
- Observing & communicating attrition rate to management if required.
- HR Budgeting and succession planning

HR Policy & Implementation

- Setting up HR policy and framework for the entire organization
- Implement & effectively communicate HR Policies, ensure compliance

Payroll/Statutory Compliances

- Responsible for time and attendance enrolment, leave management
- Salary preparation (Payroll, Contract, Interns)-Tracking monthly attendance, tracking late marking through Biometric machine, maintaining Leave register.
- Salary preparation of the staff. Responsible for processing and disbursement of Payroll(Software) and
 manually reimbursement (Such as Salary, Monthly Expenses/Allowances, Leave encashment, Incentives,
 Advances and other related aspects) and Generating salary statement and timely issuance of employee
 Pay slip.
- Responsible to update, payroll and attendance software. Ensuring updating of leave record, Muster roll (Software/Manually)
- Statutory compliances (PF, ESIC, PT) PF/ESIC account opening, withdrawal, UAN activation.
- Preparing salaries of contractual employees as per minimum wage circulars.
- Monitoring & maintaining attendance & leave records.
- Implements, maintains, and reviews payroll processing systems to ensure timely and accurate processing of payroll transactions including salaries, benefits, taxes, and other deductions.
- Ensures accurate and timely processing of payroll updates including new hires, terminations, and changes to pay rates.
- Prepares and maintains accurate records and reports of payroll transactions.
- Ensures compliance with federal, state, and local payroll, wage, and hour laws and best practices.
- Facilitates audits by providing records and documentation to auditors.

HR Operations

- Maintaining employee's personal files and records.
- Maintain the staffing report & share weekly updates with management.
- Issuing of staff uniforms & record management.
- Creation of employees Biometric ID.
- Issuing mobiles, sim-cards, I-Cards, laptop/desktop etc. to the new recruits.
- Induction, Onboarding & off-boarding.
- Send on-boarding and welcome email to introduce new joiner to the organization
- Manage email distribution list, extension list.
- Handling of staff bank account opening.
- Preparing various letters like offer letter, appointment letter, confirmation letter, increment letter, warning letter, experience, relieving letter, employee of the month, internal circulars.

- Preparing employment contract and job descriptions, on-boarding & off-boarding formalities and documentation.
- Communication and coordination- Develop internal correspondence that facilitates effective communication and transfer of information between various department heads.
- Handling of internal & external audits.
- Consult to business as a trusted HR advisor and develop and execute HR solutions that address critical organizational issues.
- Gain understanding of business priorities and align HR solutions and programs to support business.
- Build appropriate organizational relationships to enable a collaborative partnership with management, and employees
- Effectively partner with various personalities across multiple levels of the organization and influence decision-making.

Training & Development

- Assessing Training & Developmental needs of each employee by discussing with departmental heads
- Developing & maintaining the training schedule.
- Plan training programs & develop a network of trainers & experts.
- Coordinate/Arrange training whenever required & collecting the Feedback.
- Training & Certification Management. Developing clear policies and ensuring policy awareness.
- Coordinating with the External Trainers regarding Training schedule, workshops, and seminars.

Performance Management System/Appraisals

- Developing & Implementing performance management policies & processes.
- Developing formats of PMS documents required timely completion of the Performance Appraisal Assessment.
- Conduct employee satisfaction surveys and make sure the resources complete all the internal surveys.
- Review contracts & performance of staff periodically.
- Devise a framework for appraisals
- Discuss employees' career development paths with managers
- Ensuring employee satisfaction & conducting exit interviews.
- Assisting employees & hence the organization to develop & achieve the goal.

Employee Relations & Employee Engagement

- Maintaining all records of audits & documents related to HR.
- Developing administrative systems & working out compensation for all job positions & revising if required.
- SPOC for HR-related queries, issues, grievances, etc.
- Resolving employee queries by investigating issues, evaluating the situation and providing advice, HR policy guidance and leadership on path forward.
- Drive effective feedbacks for new hires.
- Plan quarterly team outing, employee engagement activities, annual functions.
- Handling celebrations of staff birthdays, farewells, monthly lunch etc. Sending emails of birthday wishes.
- Grievance handling mechanism
- Support taking disciplinary action if required.

Educational Qualification:

PGDBA + MBA HR MIT- PUNE (Year 2013)

Home Science (B.HSc) (Nutrition & Dietetics) S.M.R.K.College, Nashik, Mumbai University (Year 2006)